[SPEAKER_02]: Now, go to your bed over there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Come on.
[SPEAKER_02]: Go to your bed.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what did we say?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, we were going to talk about
[SPEAKER_01]: There are certain aspects of meditation that I think probably most people think about.
[SPEAKER_01]: When they think meditation, they'll be thinking about, so let's say, focusing on something.
[SPEAKER_02]: In the beginning, when you start practicing...
[SPEAKER_02]: I know I did, because that's the first thing you come across.
[SPEAKER_02]: The idea of meditation is the idea of concentration in terms of focusing, focusing, focusing, and then expecting the result to sort of come automatically out of you, just doing this method of focusing.
[SPEAKER_01]: I guess, first of all, the idea was focusing your attention on this sort of triangle here, around your nose, where breathing is happening.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're basically just sort of focusing on the process of breathing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And doing it as a kind of observing air passing over this area.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then it was like... and then the idea was like... smaller and smaller and smaller.
[SPEAKER_01]: You get that... that area becomes smaller and smaller and smaller until... until you're focusing on... focusing on just a pinpoint.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And what were you thinking, like, while you were doing the focus?
[SPEAKER_01]: I said I should be doing... what am I doing?
[SPEAKER_02]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: When you were doing the focusing practice, what were your thoughts in terms of... what were you thinking that you were focusing on?
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that was the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was spending most of the time wondering about that, what it was that I was supposed to be focusing on and what I was doing and whether I was doing it right and
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the meditation was, okay, what are you focusing on here?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the idea, I guess, was, what was being encouraged, was a kind of, I would say, like an objective sideways view on... Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: On the air that happens to be passing this area here.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not me breathing, but this sort of... As if you can perceive things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's no mental problem with any focusing practice.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whatever the technique might be, if it's a technique of observation and focusing and sort of preying upon moments, as the sutra would sort of describe it, the problem with that is you assume this external world independent of your perception, yet the only way you can relate to it is to perceive it, as in the experience it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you assume, through experiencing it,
[SPEAKER_02]: that it's outside of your experience and you can be objective about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But how can you even conceive the idea of outside of my experience unless you're thinking it experientially, so to speak?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you're contradicting on both fronts.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's the sole problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mind picks the dhammas to look at.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's that's just how it works.
[SPEAKER_02]: Are you assuming that those things stand for that which they cannot stand for?
[SPEAKER_02]: Such as an external world, independent of me, that is subjected to these scientific laws of impermanence.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, the Buddha and the science are saying the same thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: All these views that you hear today are completely misguided, because they're rooted in this utter assumption of
[SPEAKER_01]: But is it... you're... you're focusing on something objective.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, there's this objective flow of air that happens to be going through this... through this objective nose on the front of my face.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But also, you're... there's this kind of... you have to sort of stand back and look at it from a position of objectivity.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're...
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is very subjective.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even arahant doesn't become purely objective, because that's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_02]: That means, like, stepping outside of the aggregates and being there with objective matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_02]: He just stops appropriating his subjectivity.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why arahant still has, like, the individuality in terms of a character, a habit, and all these things.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's an allusion in greed, aversion, delusion, of course.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, yeah, people find subjectivity to be the problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it is a problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then, instead of understanding
[SPEAKER_02]: Truly, what is the problematic aspect of subjectivity and then abandoning that?
[SPEAKER_02]: They think you can simply replace subjectivity by emulating this assumption of objectivity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Isn't the kind of idea trying to get rid of the... Basically, there's always a point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can't have an experience without a point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whereas many attitudes towards meditation are kind of trying to negate that, trying to forget that, trying to take a third-person perspective or like a God's eye view on... Sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, we can do the same as what we've done before.
[SPEAKER_02]: Let's take focusing now.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, focus on your body touching the chair, like right now.
[SPEAKER_02]: What are the characteristics of that?
[SPEAKER_02]: How would you describe it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you asked me to focus on my body, get on the chair, and I just sort of looked into something that was already there, it's already kind of given this sense of...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I can feel something, but it's totally inseparable from the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like... Yeah, like the chair touching my body, or my body touching the chair.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just this kind of...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you're focusing on...
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm focusing as well.
[SPEAKER_02]: You realize you can only focus on something that's already there, given.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, now you have a choice.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yeah, you focus on it, as in, you bring your attention to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But now you have a choice.
[SPEAKER_02]: I have a choice.
[SPEAKER_02]: You have... Everybody has a choice.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that choice is...
[SPEAKER_02]: I can now continue
[SPEAKER_02]: Just keep repeating this focusing mechanically.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or, I can try to understand the nature of that thing that's necessary for my focus.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you could see those those two are mutually exclusive directions.
[SPEAKER_02]: If I keep... Oh, but I'm touching the chair.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm touching the chair.
[SPEAKER_02]: Means you're actively avoiding the direction of...
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, you're touching the chair.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, let it be there, so you get to understand
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is all the other kind of things we discussed in other videos.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can only really focus on something, attend to something, if it was given as a possibility.
[SPEAKER_02]: And by that, I mean, if it's given beforehand.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's already there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, you were able to turn to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's that peripheral aspect of, oh, it's already there without me being, without directly attending it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's already there as a possibility.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you can get to understand it and then you realize, okay, so that's all you need to do.
[SPEAKER_02]: Stop regarding it as mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you can forget all the focusing you want.
[SPEAKER_02]: Done.
[SPEAKER_02]: You fulfill the purpose of your focusing.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if your purpose is just to focus for the sake of focusing,
[SPEAKER_02]: So, actively, then, avoiding understanding things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, so, focusing...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, people are like...
[SPEAKER_01]: Going in a particular direct, you said, mutually exclusive direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, focusing in on this mechanical particular thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, there's one particular thing, and then, and then, and later, there are the next particular thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's sort of the same.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, focusing, as a rule of thumb, follows the the ideal of attending to the particular at the expense of everything else.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why it's a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because understanding is always rooted in the totality of your experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: In a
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why the whole point is, like, yeah, any form of focusing is already singling out particular.
[SPEAKER_02]: But obviously, within that particular, you can go even further.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you choosing to attend your body position, seated on the chair, it's a particular thing you focused on.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's more than sufficient.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, you want to understand the nature of that thing that you focused on, that is still there, because you brought your attention to it, and you don't need to keep holding on to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if I ask you, are you still touching the chair?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, of course.
[SPEAKER_02]: You wouldn't, hold on, I need to figure that out.
[SPEAKER_02]: Recall the memory.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: The knowledge is still there, because you attended it, you clarified it, but simply by focusing on it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But instead of that, then people who follow the rule of focusing
[SPEAKER_02]: That's generally the idea.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the idea.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's how you arrive at some sort of knowledge.
[SPEAKER_02]: You realize...
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why I ask you, what do you think that you're focusing on?
[SPEAKER_02]: What can you focus on?
[SPEAKER_02]: You can only focus on a possibility that has presented itself as being able to focus.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which means, when you start practicing this focusing upon focusing, and you actually develop a belief that you are focusing on the actual rūpa, on the actual matter, on the actual objectivity, while in reality, all you can focus is on your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_02]: In other words, your thoughts give you the focus that you can focus on.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, when you are thinking about the objective matter, you're thinking about a thought that has fully misconceived the nature of matter and presented itself as that which is the matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's like the essence of Mūla Parīyāya Sutta.
[SPEAKER_02]: Obviously, taken in a very extreme sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the point is, even... doesn't matter how far you're committed in your focusing practice, how specifically, how particularly you're staring at things, all you can do is focus at the risen dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's not, oh, I must stop doing that.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: All I have to stop doing is stop misconceiving that my thoughts can stand for that objective world, which I keep sort of fueling, the assumption of it, through this practice of focusing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because I am thinking of getting closer to the pure materiality or something, that will then free me from any subjectivity.
[SPEAKER_01]: And basically, the Buddha's teaching is not about just...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's about understanding what the dhamma is.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all about understanding
[SPEAKER_01]: So, some people...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think that can vary.
[SPEAKER_01]: They'll respond and say, well, hang on, no, but I get lots of benefit from my meditation practice, which is focusing on... Small things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Small things, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Particular things, more and more particular.
[SPEAKER_01]: I notice, the more I do it, the more refined and the more subtle, the more particular things, things I've never noticed before, I start to notice and that means awareness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, where is the nature of things found?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what is it that keeps people doing this?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why do people... why do so many people keep going in that direction?
[SPEAKER_02]: It's deeply rooted view that you get rid of your atavāda by cancelling it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You get... you overcome
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, that's on a more immediate level.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm talking about the view.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the point here, when you mentioned, like, when you're getting deeper into things, that's usually the belief.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you're not getting... you can't get deep.
[SPEAKER_02]: You always remain on the surface.
[SPEAKER_02]: Perception will always remain perceiving the perception.
[SPEAKER_02]: Perception cannot really bring you into the matter, because that would mean that you can access rūpa, which the Buddha says is inaccessible.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can only find the footing in your experience through providing a basis of misconceiving.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it feels like...
[SPEAKER_01]: It feels like you're getting deeper and deeper.
[SPEAKER_02]: You always remain there.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't matter how far you got focused.
[SPEAKER_02]: You realize all I'm focusing is on the dhammas.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's another thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it doesn't matter if it's this particular level or this particular level.
[SPEAKER_02]: The nature remains the same.
[SPEAKER_02]: Your pursuit of focusing is endless.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you're saying you're delighting in the novelty of an object.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, this feels novel.
[SPEAKER_01]: This feels like I'm noticing things I've never noticed before, which means I must be learning things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, that's... if you were to, like...
[SPEAKER_02]: I remember for myself, you start and it's kind of... feels like a novelty, feels like...
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you're so focused on particular movements.
[SPEAKER_02]: Basically, you're kind of exercising this sort of contrived sense of control.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you can only sustain that so far.
[SPEAKER_02]: But initially, it creates this sense of novelty whereby, oh, wow, I'm experiencing things differently.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But again... New things are happening.
[SPEAKER_02]: It feels good.
[SPEAKER_02]: It feels peaceful.
[SPEAKER_02]: It feels, like, eh... less cluttered, and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, bringing attention to things feels less cluttered, feels more directional.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: But why would that then justify you constantly bring attention, bring attention, bring attention, bring attention?
[SPEAKER_02]: Means you still don't understand where that peace comes from.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's in the other talk that I explained, like, eh... the simile of the anchor.
[SPEAKER_02]: You throw the anchor, and then you let the boat sort of float around, because it's anchored.
[SPEAKER_02]: So you know it can't go too far, you allow it to move around.
[SPEAKER_02]: The idea of focusing, it's like, throw the anchor, pull the anchor, throw the anchor, throw the anchor, throw the anchor, throw the anchor.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm focusing, I'm focusing, I'm focusing.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the whole point of doing the focusing practice would be, you just want pleasure, or you just want to avoid any liability to suffering, to discomfortable feelings, to uncomfortable feelings.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it becomes a management to your liability to suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or, if I focus hard enough, basically, I won't think about
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's what I was saying in the other talk.
[SPEAKER_02]: The idea of concentration, for most people, it's like you focus so hard on one point, where you forget everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why, you know, everyone calls it absorption.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's a good thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Absorbed.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're absorbed in something, that means you're basically... Unmindful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you're not aware of anything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But one-pointedness, as we described before, it's the point that includes everything else, regardless of the content.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's exactly what we described.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you focus on your experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_02]: My experience now, I'm focusing on being seated on the chair.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay?
[SPEAKER_02]: You brought your attention to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, that's the container for your context.
[SPEAKER_02]: Let's see what comes up with it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, so, while I'm seated on the chair, we're talking about these various ideas that are wrong, that are rooted in wrong assumptions, while I'm seated on the chair.
[SPEAKER_02]: While I'm seated on the chair, I have these feelings arising.
[SPEAKER_02]: While I'm seated on the chair, I have these other thoughts arising, while I'm seated on the chair.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, if you're doing the focusing practice, you'll be ignoring all these things that are happening, but I'm sitting in the chair, I'm sitting, I'm touching, touching, leaning, leaning, touching, touching, leaning, thinking, thinking.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, so you're not sitting on the chair.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, you are, but now you forgot that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you think the whole purpose is just to be fully absorbed in focusing right in front of you.
[SPEAKER_02]: And how can you then be fully absorbed in what's in front of you, without doing that at the expense of the nature?
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's not in front of you.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's that's why it's inherently wrong.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't do it right.
[SPEAKER_02]: You cannot have the right outcome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Canceling out the context.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're basically saying, I'm not interested.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's again, like people, probably many people...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm all about content.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm just interested, delighting in... in the next thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's another sort of the people, you know, probably many people read, but they would not necessarily see a connection with this, what we're talking about.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is that that one where he says, all this Samādhi
[SPEAKER_02]: But what they do, it's like a like a like an owl praying upon, like waiting for a fish.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or a jackal waiting for a... For the next meal.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, imagine, just don't take my word for it, imagine if you were a hunter.
[SPEAKER_02]: To catch it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, eh... when the Buddha described them, when he said all these people call themselves meditators, but all they do, they are like a jackal trying to catch a prey.
[SPEAKER_02]: They call themselves... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, basically, trying to catch, trying to focus and catch and attend and grab the moment, whatever you want to call it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And he said, whoever does that, does so rooted in sensuality.
[SPEAKER_02]: They meditate with sensuality, because you meditate with that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, oh, this is on the basis of my senses, sense of touch, sense of... usually sense of touch, but sensibly can be visual, whatever else, audible.
[SPEAKER_02]: The point is, you're catching the moment that you believe, that it has significance for you, profound significance, you yourself kind of gave it, in a way, with your wrong views, that if you catch the moment rightly,
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't need to think about it or address it on an every single basis.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, focus, focus, focus, focus, focus.
[SPEAKER_02]: Got it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I got the moment.
[SPEAKER_02]: I had this great experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: My body felt so light.
[SPEAKER_02]: It was like disappearing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, so that must mean that I've succeeded somehow.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's usually like, I had experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, now I have to interpret it, which means I have no understanding of experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now I have to fabricate it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because even if you have the lofty, unusual experience,
[SPEAKER_02]: What's the nature of it?
[SPEAKER_02]: It means slightly less common experience of this body here, as opposed to more common daily experience of this body here.
[SPEAKER_02]: Either way, there is this body here.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, normally people would think you do the meditation, but then afterwards you'll have this profound experience, and then you have to make... you have to interpret that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Make sense out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that actual making sense out of it, that's the meditation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's when you start... Well, that's closer to what meditation is.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the direction that you need to be going in.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, the best
[SPEAKER_02]: Jhāna is.
[SPEAKER_02]: I keep thinking about it, dwelling on it.
[SPEAKER_02]: The monk enters it.
[SPEAKER_02]: By not dwelling on the theme of jhāna, he doesn't develop it.
[SPEAKER_02]: As simple as that.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, with the whole sort of, you know, commentarial evolutionary take of watching nostrils leads to absorption, leads to jhāna, leads to what not.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ānāpānasati Sutta doesn't talk about jhānas at all.
[SPEAKER_02]: It talks about four foundations of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, practice mindfulness of the breathing
[SPEAKER_02]: I think there's some sort of mystical absorption of focusing.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it disappears, you just, like, lose all senses.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that was the meditation of breathing by myself.
[SPEAKER_02]: While I'm sitting here, I have such and such feeling arising and enduring.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I still feel like that while I'm sitting here, while we're talking about these themes.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I don't need to try to catch anything, actually.
[SPEAKER_02]: All you need to do is stay at the doorway, which is you determine through your initial act of focusing, of, oh, this is my situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: My situation is being
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Within that, now, everything that happens will happen within it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you don't need to chase it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And counter-symbolism is the good gate.
[SPEAKER_02]: But usually, it's the one the man sort of surveys the outskirts of the city.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's no any in and out way, entry or exit, except one.
[SPEAKER_02]: Big gate.
[SPEAKER_02]: And he decides, oh, if I stay at the gate, I'll know whoever's in and I'll know whoever's out.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't need to chase people individually in or try to get them outside.
[SPEAKER_02]: I just need to stay here.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the idea of... how do you stay here while things are changing?
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not by focusing, focusing, focusing, focusing.
[SPEAKER_02]: It means, I'm at the gate, I'm at the gate, I'm at the gate, I'm at the gate, I'm at... people coming in and out, but you're looking at the gate.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: You stay by understanding this.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, this is the... this is the present container, this is the entry and exit point.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'll keep that in mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's samādhi.
[SPEAKER_02]: Keeping things in mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Keeping things together, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Samādhi.
[SPEAKER_02]: Composing, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Composing things
[SPEAKER_02]: attending to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yeah, don't be completely mindless and non-attentive.
[SPEAKER_02]: But doing attention for the sake of attention means actually ignoring the situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: You cannot do... you cannot attend to that which is peripheral to what you're attending.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I'm attending to this means and other things that are there simultaneously present cannot be attended to.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's not the point to attend all of them.
[SPEAKER_02]: The point is that what you attend
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, the nature of your experience involves the presence of other things, this periphery, this, like, other things that you aren't attending to right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you're... Of course, when I ask you to focus on your body, for example, I could ask you to focus on something else.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's equally... that can serve as a footing for anchoring.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, like, so, any meditation that avoids this kind of...
[SPEAKER_01]: That avoids acknowledging the periphery of whatever it is you're attending to.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's going to be missing the whole nature of your experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's going to be like a jackal trying upon and ignoring everything else.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like a cat catching the fish and ignoring everything else.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the Buddha mocked it.
[SPEAKER_02]: He said, with his shoulders drooping, head swinging, basically, sleeping, drooling.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm a meditator.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm a meditator because I have this powerful concentration where I
[SPEAKER_01]: Isn't that funny?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's generally... that is the... that is actually the nature of falling asleep.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you fall asleep... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything else gets excluded.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything... yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're lying on your bed and you're thinking about whatever it is you're thinking about.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, at some point, you forget the background where you... oh, I'm lying in my bed in here.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you're done.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you're absorbed in the particular thoughts.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why even in your dreams, if you end up in a dream, something
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, you just remember where you are.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, we can't.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't even sleep while I'm lying here.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what waking is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, so basically, the common idea about what meditation is, is very similar to what happens when you fall asleep.
[SPEAKER_02]: In a way, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, in a way, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I think it has similar physical manifestations as well.
[SPEAKER_02]: But another thing that often gets tied with this folksy practice is the idea of sensations.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: As if some sort of a hybrid phenomena that's kind of in between perception and
[SPEAKER_01]: Another thing that I used to do, I think a lot of people do, is, yeah, so focusing on sensations in the body with the rationale that that's what the Buddha meant by vedanā.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then when we describe them vedanā, he said, well, they are pleasant, unpleasant, neutral.
[SPEAKER_02]: So what difference does it make if your sensation is in your elbows or your shoulders?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it can't be...
[SPEAKER_02]: Either way, feeling is cetasika, as the Buddha said in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's mental, always mental.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you observing, observing, there you go, observing sensation in your legs, means you're perceiving sense of touch in your legs.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: That then, somehow, starts to stand for the feeling, vedanā.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, how can you perceive vedanā?
[SPEAKER_02]: How is that possible?
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm perceiving what I'm feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the Buddha said, feeling is that which feels, that it's felt, and perception is that which perceives, that's perceived.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, how can you then perceive what you feel?
[SPEAKER_01]: The sensations are usually described as, like... Well, from the point of view of perception, they're described as feelings.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you look at feelings, they're described as perceptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you will maintain that ambiguity, that confusion, that contradiction, because you don't clarify what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when people are...
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nobody denies the existence of sensations.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or that which you refer to as sensations.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's the confusion that you imply with it, as if that which you're perceiving is your feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, all I need to do is stop ignoring how I... well, start ignoring or maintain the ignorance of how I'm actually feeling, and keep hoping for the right perception that will reveal the nature of feeling and everything else to me, because you assume that it can be perceived.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yeah, you can...
[SPEAKER_02]: I have various sensations in my back, after, you know, a bee stings you.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's not how I feel.
[SPEAKER_02]: Those are things that I perceive, because the body is spatial, three-dimensional, it has the insides, has the outsides, and, you know, touch receptors go both ways.
[SPEAKER_02]: So you can feel internal sort of perceptions, which are sensations.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then you saying that that's what your feelings are,
[SPEAKER_02]: That's how you maintain the wrong view.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because feelings are felt on the level of the mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why we start with, like, what's your mood right now?
[SPEAKER_02]: That's where the feelings are.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, I'm feeling pleasure in my hand.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: You have agreeable perceptions in your hand that result in experience of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's not how you must stop paying attention to sensations.
[SPEAKER_01]: Feelings in my body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Feelings being in a place.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Feelings are placed in this body.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then you can measure the feeling by the means of perceptions.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was like a surgery I had in my hand.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they sort of put the area, they numbed it out, so you don't feel anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But they would numb it out, and I could feel them putting on the tendons, which is not something that is agreeable to me.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I could feel that, and I thought, ah, it's not numb enough, because I feel pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: I feel pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I'm sensing only the putting of the tendon, which is disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, they would numb it out even more.
[SPEAKER_00]: And still, the pain was there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I realized, oh, wait, they can't numb that out.
[SPEAKER_00]: They cannot numb.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's how people experience pain in their limbs after they lost a whole limb.
[SPEAKER_02]: Wrecking, unbearable pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because of the feeling, in regard to... That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Feeling is always phantom, from the point of view of perception.
[SPEAKER_02]: Feeling can never enter the domain of perception.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you have feeling, perception and intention are impossible to disjoin, as the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, whenever there is a perception, there is a simultaneously present enduring feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: Disagreeable perception, but then some people will find that pleasurable.
[SPEAKER_02]: There are people who find pain being... discomfort, extreme, piercing discomfort being inflicted upon the body, they find pleasure in it.
[SPEAKER_02]: There are other people who have extreme amount of comfort afflicted
[SPEAKER_02]: So, mind determines, basically, the threshold of what's going to be painful or not.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hence, the, you know, the trained body, the body resistant to elements, can endure much more.
[SPEAKER_02]: The mind developed in jhānas can endure the roughness of the root of a tree, horrible fermented urine for the medicine, rough hemp robes, will be like silk and basmati rice in the king's palace.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's how it will be felt.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why Buddha said you should practice jhāna and develop your mind, in that sense, correct sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you think that you can actually perceive your feelings, well, you're completely... it's uncalled for, but you end up giving significance to your perception that doesn't deserve.
[SPEAKER_02]: It shouldn't be there.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's misconceiving it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you don't need to deny sensations, or say sensations are wrong.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just need to understand them.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you'll see, if you're either taking them as perceptions that stand in for feelings, or feelings that stand for perceptions, or both.
[SPEAKER_02]: But once you clarify them, you won't do that anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can still use it as a designation and a form of speech.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, I've got sensations in my leg.
[SPEAKER_02]: I've got to change my posture.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you aren't going to find vedanā by focusing?
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because what you can focus on is what you can observe.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you can't observe feelings, you can only feel them.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if your only means of any form of effort is on the level of focusing, focusing means this whole domain of what's being felt right there simultaneously with it is invisible to you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Knowledge, however,
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a blanket access to all of the domains.
[SPEAKER_02]: Nature of... understanding the nature of things that you're not directly focusing on, but discerning it as a necessary basis, means it's base for understanding intention, feeling, and perception, for that matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, yeah, you can use a base of perception to establish anchoring of your mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, for example,
[SPEAKER_02]: So, whatever you do, whatever we say, whatever you feel, whatever... whichever way your body moves, it's done within the container of the light that still endures.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's not a new.
[SPEAKER_02]: You didn't create this light.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is there a reason they provide a basis for the whole experience on a more particular level that's happening to you?
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's not something I can focus on, because I can't see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you do anchoring properly, you do focusing properly, it's something you don't focus on anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, focusing means bringing attention to it, but doesn't
[SPEAKER_01]: Even... so, even perceptions aren't really things that I'm attending... attending to.
[SPEAKER_02]: Any of the aggregates for that matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like... That's why the Buddha, as you said in the last talk...
[SPEAKER_01]: I attend to these things, but within that I can...
[SPEAKER_01]: I can discern various perceptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're all with peripherals.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you have a view that you must attend and focus, you have a view that prioritizes the content.
[SPEAKER_02]: It has to be done at the expense of the nature.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whatever aggregate of perception...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, whatever perception... old, new, past, future, far, near, up, down, left, right... Whatever particularly the perception might be, he knows perception is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: He doesn't go, oh, this is... No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Perception is there because it has to be in some way.
[SPEAKER_02]: And so, you stop being concerned about what way perception is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know perception is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whatever feeling...
[SPEAKER_02]: Past, present, future, far or near, personal, impersonal, pleasant, unpleasant feeling is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, every aggregate can be... is present particularly, but if that's all you see, you're ignorant of its nature.
[SPEAKER_02]: Means you're ignorant of the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's why focusing outlines the picture for you, but understanding
[SPEAKER_02]: Manasikāra is on the level of the opposite of what you're attending.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why yoniso.
[SPEAKER_02]: Manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_02]: From the origin.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, knowing the origin of this very thing that I'm attending, while this origin of that attention is present.
[SPEAKER_02]: How can you attend the origin of your attention?
[SPEAKER_02]: You won't attend it.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: That is inconceivable, but I will know that there is that because of which I'm able to see that I cannot see, but I can know that it's there as a necessary basis, namely the I.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's properly exercised yoniso manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's all in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I guess most people would think yoniso means attending carefully, attending... that kind of thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, you can attend it carefully on the level of nature of things, not on the level of what you can, like, observe and stare.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if it's the origin of my attention, how can that same attention attend itself in its origin?
[SPEAKER_02]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the only reason you would keep assuming that is because
[SPEAKER_00]: Context of potential.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, yeah, pretty much.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_02]: Can you attend something from nothingness?
[SPEAKER_02]: No, but it needs to be there, beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that context is the origin of this thing, in a sense that this thing couldn't be what it is without this whole larger context being there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, attend to your elbows touching the chair.
[SPEAKER_02]: How can you do that if you wouldn't have elbows?
[SPEAKER_02]: There is no chair.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you're not sitting and
[SPEAKER_02]: If it's already there, enduring.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when you attend to any aspect, it's not new.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not begun.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's been going on and on and on.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's there, enduring.
[SPEAKER_02]: Fully understand that, that's how you also become unable to regard the most volitional choice, decision, as mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you see it fully encapsulated within that which cannot be yours.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you can only choose what's already there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the option to choose a certain choice is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you choose it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That choice has always been there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, or you can even look.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm still sitting here.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'm still... the choice to sit here is still going on.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if you say now, oh, but I have a choice to stand up and change that situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you can only do that because there is a possibility for you, as in for the body, to be moved in an upright position.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you... when you stand up, you just exercise another choice on top of the choice that's been exercised of you sitting.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, there's no amount of... there is no such choice that can take you outside of the given container of your experience as a whole, from which you can really impartially or independently or like as a master choose without any basis for that choice.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's always secondary to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the choice... the effects of your choice
[SPEAKER_02]: The results of your action are within your experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_02]: They're secondary to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if I choose to stand up, I've changed my initially determined sort of base for my mindfulness that I focused on initially to just discern it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But now, I can only change it because there is another potential basis that this can be replaced with.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hence, the four body postures.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there's no fifth, by the way.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're either going to be standing, laying down, walking or sitting.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's when you start realizing that it doesn't matter how much I exercise my choice within this, it's going to be within some limiting container.
[SPEAKER_02]: Fundamentally, that limiting container is the five aggregates or the life in itself.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't do anything unless you're alive.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, am I still alive?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's your... the most general container.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if that's taken away, which can be at any
[SPEAKER_02]: And if that goes, none of this can remain.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you keep that context in your mind, that's basically maraṇasati, done correctly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Everything is then put against the backdrop of
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if you're the owner, you're the master, you're the controller, you're in charge of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: How can you be in charge of something you can't even imagine?
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't even know the ending that's going to, you know... Well, you can know that it's going to end.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's good, but... Because it hasn't originated from you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is it already falling apart?
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's beyond, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's beyond you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Inaccessible.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: That it's the murderer waiting to, you know, stab you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's the impermanence.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's anicca.
[SPEAKER_02]: Unownable.
[SPEAKER_02]: Anicca means impossible to own.
[SPEAKER_02]: Impossible to be mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: And but if it's unownable, and yet here I am, depending on it, there's suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's unownable, it is dukkha.
[SPEAKER_02]: If it's unownable and dukkha, then
[SPEAKER_02]: This sense of myself, I don't own even that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if it's unownable in dukkha, then my experience is anatta.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't need to do anatta then.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, this is impermanence, this is suffering, and this is the not-self.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: This is impermanence, this is suffering, this experience is experienced as not-self.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you see your sense of self as
[SPEAKER_02]: Even in your imagination, then your sense of self, right here and there, will be felt as not my sense of self.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, atta and anatta means to basically my self or not my self.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it doesn't mean there's no self, because if there is no self, what are you designating by saying there is no self?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like allowing that understanding to endure long enough in the background.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: To kind of color.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ignoring that, then, takes you in the direction of, oh, I am doing this, in the sense of, I am the controller, master of this.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, okay, so what do you do next?
[SPEAKER_02]: Nothing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Clarify that same thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what you do next.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just allow it to endure, and make it clearer, and clearer, and clearer, and harder, and harder to forget.
[SPEAKER_02]: That doesn't matter how much I'm involved, how involved I get with things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Simultaneously present is the basis for those things, that it's inaccessible to me.
[SPEAKER_02]: And when I say basis of those things, I mean basis for your own life as well, because your life is another thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you couldn't see how that this contemplation
[SPEAKER_02]: How can you exercise passion towards this, when you cannot possibly, like, lose the sight of the context that it's inherently inaccessible to you, unownable, not worth the effort?
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's when one says, like, when the monk practices rightly, he starts developing these notions that, oh, this is not worth engaging with.
[SPEAKER_02]: This is not worth delighting here.
[SPEAKER_02]: I can still do it, but now the
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you were finding it worthy of doing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Passionate about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Passionate about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Delighting in it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: It becomes impossible.
[SPEAKER_02]: Passion is worthless.
[SPEAKER_02]: Effort of investing passion becomes inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether I delight in it or not, it is what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's going to... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you don't need to, oh, I must stop.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just don't lose the sight of that peripheral context.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't matter what you are particularly attending.
[SPEAKER_02]: Neither it's on the context of being all rooted in something that I cannot even conceive owning.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, pleasure pain stops bothering me.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that delight just naturally falls off.
[SPEAKER_01]: Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to kind of fight the delight.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just kind of stop... Yeah, you just need to maintain the context in face of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if all you're doing is focusing on what's in front of you, means your mind will be fully taken by pleasure, fully taken by pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you'll be resisting the pain, prolonging pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: That will always be peripheral, which is, you've chosen not to look.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: The knowledge is on the level of peripheral.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if you have to keep keeping things that you know in your mind, means you haven't really understood them.
[SPEAKER_02]: You have to keep reminding yourself, because if you forget, the knowledge goes with it, which means that's not knowledge.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like the Buddha, in the simile, when a man asked him, when he asked the Buddha, do you always prepare these answers beforehand?
[SPEAKER_02]: When people ask him, he said, well, let me ask you in return.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're a master chariot maker, or whatever he was.
[SPEAKER_02]: If I were to ask you anything about the workings of the chariots or parts, would you need to prepare the answer?
[SPEAKER_02]: He said, well, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: People wake me up in the middle of the night and ask me a question, I'll give them the answer right away, because I have fully understood how a chariot works.
[SPEAKER_02]: All the engineering, the dynamics, it's just fully understood.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's that dhamma is always the same.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's how Tathāgata doesn't prepare the answers.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you understood it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you... Again, similar to the same chariot-maker.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you haven't understood how the chariot actually works, but you read about it, then you...
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, so the wheels, the wheels, the wheels in the chassis, okay, the seat... You have to think about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: You stop thinking about it, gone.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, oh God, how does it work?
[SPEAKER_02]: How does it work again?
[SPEAKER_02]: It means you haven't understood it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's not a big surprise, then, when you read the suttas, that that's all the Buddha talks about.
[SPEAKER_02]: Dhamma is all about understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah?
[SPEAKER_02]: You attend certain things at the expense of others.
[SPEAKER_02]: As in, things that are conducive to non-lust, at the expense of things that are conducive to lust.
[SPEAKER_02]: But only so that you can understand the nature of them as they are.
[SPEAKER_00]: Discerning the nature that is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: That thing is there, like nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, the element of nibbāna, that's what it means.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't mean you're already in nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: It means the possibility of you developing the dhamma of nibbāna is possible.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you do it right.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not something that you...
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not outside of your five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's basically the attitude in regard to the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a particular dhamma of complete absence of passion in regard to the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why even Putujana does that in Majjhima thirty... No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: Later on.
[SPEAKER_02]: But he says, when he talks about the conceiving, I am doing this, I'm attaining this, and he says, at some point, some man can even say, oh, this is nibbāna, and I'm attaining this nibbāna, and this nibbāna is mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: And people think, oh, it must be not the real nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then the Buddha says, no, it is the real nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: What this man asserts is that which nibbāna is.
[SPEAKER_02]: But he doesn't attain it, as in he doesn't actually develop it properly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the element of nibbāna is basically the experience of absence of greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what nibbāna is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And one can discern that.
[SPEAKER_02]: One can discern that, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: The more you discern it, the more the context will endure.
[SPEAKER_02]: The more the context will endure, the less of you maintaining all these random passions will occur.
[SPEAKER_02]: And when those passions completely go, then, on account of the context that you started discerning, you are then in nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what Sotāpanna understood, basically, in Nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: He understands the arahant.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, he needs to develop it.
[SPEAKER_02]: He needs to maintain that context, simply through non-restraint, through non-engagement with sensuality, through restraint, and that's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: He will have to arrive at the complete eradication of greed, aversion, delusion, from that context that has been fundamentally understood.
[SPEAKER_02]: The context of unownable, unpleasurable, and thus, not myself.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not my own self.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anything particular can only ever be determined by that context, but not understanding that.
[SPEAKER_02]: What do you mean?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you've uncovered the context.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you say you've uncovered the context, basically, you've just simply uncovered that which everything is... the yoniso, that which everything is determined by, whether you were aware of that or not.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: That upon which you
[SPEAKER_02]: You fully understand that, you will not be able to maintain passion, aversion, delusion, in regard to that thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.